Guide to the Jared French Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jared French papers
1921-1990
GEN MSS 732
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.97
(12 boxes) + 1 broadside
Collection contains correspondence, photographs, and other materials documenting the life and career of painter Jared French and a circle of friends and collaborators. Correspondence with individuals and cultural institutions, chiefly museums and galleries, document French's personal and professional affairs, with significant representation from members of the literary and artistic and gay male communities in New York during the middle decades of the twentieth century. In addition to large groups of letters from his wife Margaret (Hoening) French and painter Paul Cadmus, correspondents include Jack Dunphy, E. M. Forster, Edward Hopper, Lincoln Kirstein, George Platt Lynes, Bernard Perlin, George Tooker, Carl Van Vechten, Glenway Wescott, Monroe Wheeler, and Donald Windham. Photographs in the collection document French's personal relationships, interests in classical statuary and architecture, and artistic collaborations. Travel photographs depict statuary, architecture, and public scenes and events, with groups, travel companions, and friends. Some photographs appear to have been taken during the early 1950s in Europe, mostly in Italy (Florence). Others, depicting scenes in Europe, Vermont, New York City, and Coney Island, date from the 1920s through 1940s. People present include Jared and Margaret French, Paul Cadmus, E. M. Forster, Lincoln Kirstein, Osbert Sitwell, and others. Photographs from the "PaJaMa" collective formed by French with his wife and Cadmus, many of which were taken during the 1930s and 1940s on Fire Island, Provincetown, and Nantucket beaches, include George Tooker, Lincoln Kirstein, Truman Capote, George Platt Lynes, Donald Windham, Jack Dunphy, and Monroe Wheeler.
French, Jared, 1905-1988
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Elysium Press on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009 and 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 10: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Jared French (1905-1988)
Jared French, a painter who specialized in the medium of egg tempera, was part of a circle of friends and colleagues, including Paul Cadmus and George Tooker, sometimes referred to as magic realists. French received a B.A. degree from Amherst College in 1925 before moving to New York City, where he befriended Cadmus. He married artist Margaret Hoening in 1937 and, with Cadmus, they formed the PaJaMa photographic collective. French relocated to Italy in 1961, where he remained until his death in 1988.
Scope and Contents
The Jared French papers contain correspondence, photographs, and other materials documenting the life and career of artist Jared French and a circle of friends and collaborators. Correspondence with individuals and cultural institutions, chiefly museums and galleries, document French's personal and professional affairs, with significant representation from members of the literary and artistic communities in New York during the middle decades of the twentieth century. In addition to large groups of letters from his wife Margaret (Hoening) French, painter Paul Cadmus, and longtime companion Roberto Giannotta, correspondents include members of the French family, Jack Dunphy, E. M. Forster, Edward Hopper, Lincoln Kirstein, George Platt Lynes, Dan Maloney, Bernard Perlin, George Tooker, Carl Van Vechten, Glenway Wescott, Monroe Wheeler, and Donald Windham.
Over 600 photographs in the collection document French's artwork, personal relationships, interests in classical statuary and architecture, and collaborations from roughly the 1930s through 1960s. Photographs from the PaJaMa collective ("Paul, Jared, and Margaret") formed by French with his wife and Cadmus were taken during the 1930s and 1940s on Fire Island, Provincetown, and Nantucket beaches, as well as in Vermont and Hoboken. Photographs include George Tooker, Lincoln and Fidelma Kirstein, Truman Capote, George Platt Lynes, Donald Windham, Jack Dunphy, Monroe Wheeler, and others. In addition to the PaJaMa photographs, there are approximately 250 travel photographs depicting statuary, architecture, and public scenes and events, with groups, travel companions, and friends. More than half the photographs appear to have been taken during the early 1950s in Europe, mostly in Florence, Italy. Others, depicting scenes in Europe, Vermont, New York City, and Coney Island, date from the 1920s through 1940s. People present include Jared and Margaret French, Paul Cadmus, E. M. Forster, Lincoln Kirstein, Osbert Sitwell, and Jensen Yow.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1921-1989. II. Photographs, 1920s-1980. III. Personal Papers, 1925-1986. IV. 2013 Addition, 1927-1990.
Language(s)
Chiefly in English; some materials in Italian.
Art, American -- 20th Century; Artists, American -- 20th Century; Photography, Artistic; Photography, Erotic; Photographic prints; Artists; LGBTQ resource; Cadmus, Paul, 1904-1999; Capote, Truman, 1924-1984; Dunphy, Jack, 1914-; Forster, E. M. (Edward Morgan), 1879-1970; French, Jared, 1905-1988; French, Margaret; Hopper, Edward, 1882-1967; Kirstein, Lincoln, 1907-1996; Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955; Perlin, Bernard, 1918-2014; Sitwell, Osbert, 1892-1969; Tooker, George; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Wheeler, Monroe, 1899-1988; Windham, Donald
- Correspondence, 1921-1989; Series I; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, consists chiefly of incoming letters to Jared French. Letters from individuals and cultural institutions document French's personal and professional affairs, with significant representation from members of the literary and artistic communities in New York during the middle part of the twentieth century. Correspondents include his wife Margaret French, members of the French family, Paul Cadmus, Jack Dunphy, E. M. Forster, Edward Hopper, Lincoln Kirstein, George Platt Lynes, Dan Maloney, Marianne Moore, Bernard Perlin, Jerome Robbins, George Tooker, Carl Van Vechten, Glenway Wescott, Monroe Wheeler, and Donald Windham. There are also numerous folders of business correspondence from museums and galleries.
  There are scattered letters from French to others, including copies of letters from French to his father, Henry, as well as four folders of letters from Margaret French to their friend Roberto Giannotta. Outgoing letters are identified in folder notes.
  - Archives of American Art, 1972, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art International, 1967 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Students League (New York, N.Y.), 1968 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Babtkis Foundation, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes draft of letter from French
  - Banfer Gallery, 1963-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Barker, Jim, 1964 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Barnes, Grover C., 1969 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Berman, Avis, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes notes by French on Juliana Force
  - British Museum, 1968 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Browne, Turner, 1980 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cadmus, Paul, [1949?]-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
    Includes letters from Cadmus to Roberto Gionnotta and from French to Cadmus
  - Campbell, Sandy, 1943-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes letter to Margaret
  - Christopher, William, [19]67 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dunphy, Jack, [circa 1950]-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Edel, Leon, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes copy of letter from French to Edel
  - Eliasoph, Philip, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Fairleigh Dickinson University, 1966 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fonderia artistica Vincigliata, 1967 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Forster, E. M. (Edward Morgan), 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - French, Frances (sister), 1921-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - French, Henry (father), 1921-1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
  - French, Margaret (wife), 1937-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 33-44)
  - Furbank, [Philip Nicholas], 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Gaff, Lloyd, 1942-1961 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Includes photograph
  - Giannotta, Roberto, 1959-1975, undated- (Box 3, Folder 47-51)
  - Giannotta, Roberto (letters from Margaret French), 1969-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 52-55)
  - Hewitt, Ed, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Hopper, Edward, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Includes letter from Jo Hopper
  - Institute for Sex Research, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - King's College (Cambridge University), 1978 March (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1964 December 28 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Copy of letter from French to Kirstein
  - Lago, Mary, 1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Lynes, George Platt, 1943-1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Maloney, Dan, 1959-1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Midtown Galleries (New York, N.Y.), 1975-1981 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Includes drafts of letters from French to gallery
  - Monique Knowlton Gallery, 1971, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1955 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Morrin, Peter, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    Includes drafts of letters from French
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters (U.S.), 1966-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Perlin, Bernard, 1947-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Réalité Galleries, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Robbins, Jerome, 1951 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Robert Isaacson Gallery, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Robert Samuel Gallery, 1979-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Royce, Louise, 1974 August 3 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Rutgers University. Art Gallery, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Schiff, Ruth, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Schnakenberg, H. E. (Henry Ernest), 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
    Includes copy of letter from French
  - Starkowski, Ted, 1954-1977 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - [Steffler, Reinhart?], undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Syracuse University. Library. Manuscript Collections, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Thayer, Forrest, 1944 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Tooker, George, 1949, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    Includes clipping
  - University of Rochester. Memorial Art Gallery, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1939, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    Includes note to Paul Cadmus
  - Vandervall, Arthur H., 1977 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Wescott, Glenway, 1938-1944, undated (Box 4, Folder 86-87)
    Includes letters to Margaret
  - Wheeler, Monroe, 1942-1977 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    Inlcudes draft of letter from French
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1963-1981 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Windham, Donald, 1948, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Yow, [Jensen], 1960 May 30 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Others, 1932-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 92)
- Photographs, 1920s-1980; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: People, PaJaMa Photographs, Travel, Art, and Other.
  The Photographs series features 182 photographs from the PaJaMa collective ("Paul, Jared, and Margaret") formed by Paul Cadmus, Jared French, and Margaret French. Most of the PaJaMa photographs, shot in black-and-white and printed 5" x 7" or smaller, were taken during the 1930s and 1940s on Fire Island, Provincetown, and Nantucket beaches, but there are also images from Vermont and Hoboken. Photographs include the artists, George Tooker, Lincoln and Fidelma Kirstein, Truman Capote, George Platt Lynes, Donald Windham, Jack Dunphy, Monroe Wheeler, and others.
  In addition to the PaJaMa photographs, there are approximately 250 travel photographs shot in black-and-white and printed 21/2" x 3 1/2". Photographs depict statuary, architecture, and public scenes and events, with groups, travel companions, and friends. More than half the photographs appear to have been taken during the early 1950s in Europe, mostly in Italy (Florence). Others, depicting scenes in Europe, Vermont, New York City, and Coney Island, date from the 1920s through 1940s. People present include Jared and Margeret French, Paul Cadmus, E. M. Forster, Lincoln Kirstein, Osbert Sitwell, Jensen Yow, and others.
  There are also a number of photographs of original paintings and drawings by Cadmus, French and Luigi Lucioni. Other photographs include erotica, with images of French, Robert Giannotta, and others, a bullfight, and an unidentified place. Erotica can also be found in the PaJaMa photographs.
  Additional photographs documenting artwork by French and other artisits can be found in Series IV.
  - PEOPLE
    - French, Jared, 1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 93-98)
      Includes photographs by Carl Van Vechten
    - French, Margaret, undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Kirstein, Lincoln, undated (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Groups, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - PaJaMa PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Photographs, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 103-104)
    - Photographs, 1930s-1940s (Box 6, Folder 105-109)
  - TRAVEL
    - Photographs, 1920s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 110-113)
    - Photographs, 1920s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 114-126)
  - ARTWORK
    - Paul Cadmus painting of Jared French, undated (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Jared French paintings and drawings, 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 128)
      Photographs by D. James Dee
    - Luigi Lucioni painting of Jared French, undated (Box 8, Folder 129)
      Includes clipping dated 1931
    - PaJaMa drawings, undated (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - OTHERS
    - 138 [Howe?] Ave., Rutherford, N.J., 1940 June (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Bullfight, undated (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Erotica, undated (Box 8, Folder 134-136)
    - Foliage in unidentified place, undated (Box 8, Folder 137)
- Personal Papers, 1925-1986; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series III, Personal Papers, contains miscellaneous other materials, including fragments of proofs for writings by E. M. Forster and a notebook, by French, of recollections of Forster and others covering the period from 1939 to 1959.
  - Clippings, 1949-1986, undated (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 9, Folder 138a)
  - Financial records, 1958-1977 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Manuscript fragments, 1977-1981, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Notebook on E. M. Forster, [circa 1970] (Box 9, Folder 141-142)
  - Proofs for E.M. Forster texts, corrected, with proofreaders marks in unidentified hand, [1949?] (Box 9, Folder 143-144)
    Includes portions of "The New Disorder" and On Criticism in the Arts, Especially Music
  - Postcard book, "Aix-les-Bains," annotated, undated (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Printed ephemera, 1925-1980, undated (Box 9, Folder 146-147)
  - Vendor description, [2009] (Box 9, Folder 148)
- 2013 Addition, 1927-1990; Series IV; 0.63; (2 boxes) + 1 broadside
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Other Papers.
  Series IV, 2013 Addition, consists of correspondence and photographic and printed documentation of artwork. There is additional correspondence with Paul Cadmus and Lincoln Kirstein, but most correspondence found in Series IV is with galleries and musuems. The largest file relates to the Banfer Gallery in New York. Several folders containing approximately 145 photographs (including multiples) document artwork by French, Cadmus, and other artists.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - ACA Galleries, 1985 May 18 (Box 11, Folder 151)
    - Amherst College, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 152)
    - Banfer Gallery, Inc., 1964-1969, undated (Box 11, Folder 153-156)
    - Cadmus, Paul, 1984-1988, undated (Box 11, Folder 157)
    - Circus World Museum, 1971-1972, undated (Box 11, Folder 158)
    - French, Mrs. H. R., 1927-1928 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - Imago Imprint, 1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1987 February 7 (Box 11, Folder 161)
    - Madison Art Center, 1987 March 18 (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - Maroney, James, 1984, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 163)
    - Midtown Galleries (New York, N.Y.), 1985-1990, undated (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1984 March (Box 11, Folder 165)
    - National Museum of American Art (U.S.), 1984-1989, undated (Box 11, Folder 166)
    - Nelken, Axel, 1987 February 11 (Box 11, Folder 167)
    - Norton Gallery and School of Art, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 168)
    - Sid Deutsch Gallery (New York, N.Y.), 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 169)
    - Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1985 June 13 (Box 11, Folder 170)
    - Sutherland, David, 1984-1986, undated (Box 11, Folder 171)
    - United States. Treasury Dept., 1937 (Box 11, Folder 172)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1986 May 13 (Box 11, Folder 173)
    - Others, 1982-1988, undated (Box 11, Folder 174)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Artwork documentation, 1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 175-177)
      Includes photographs of artwork by Oliver Baker, Geoffrey Clements, D. James Dee, and others
    - Artwork documentation, undated (Box 12, Folder 178-180)
    - Clippings, 1939-1972, undated (Box 12, Folder 181)
      General
      Also stored in: 13 (Broadside)
    - Manuscript notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - "Model Trouble," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - Clipping, 1941 January 4 (Box 13 (Broadside))
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 10: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Clippings (In Series I) (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Proofs (In Series III) (Box 10, Folder 150)